The story I wanted to share with you today
القصة التي أريد أن أشاركها معكم اليوم
is my challenge as an Iranian artist,
هو تحدي كوني فنانه إيرانية،
as an Iranian woman artist,
كفنانة إيرانية،
living in exile.
تعيش في المنفى.
Well, it has its pluses and minuses.
حسنا ، لها إيجابياتها وسيئاتها.
On the dark side,
على الجانب المظلم،
politics doesn't seem to escape people like me.
السياسة لا تبدو كمهرب لناس من أمثالي.
Every Iranian artist, in one form or another,
كل فنان إيراني، بشكل أو آخر،
is political.
هو سياسي.
Politics have defined our lives.
وقد حددت السياسة حياتنا.
If you're living in Iran,
إذا كنت تعيش في إيران،
you're facing censorship, harassment,
انت تواجه الرقابة، والمضايقات،
arrest, torture --
الاعتقال والتعذيب --
at times, execution.
في بعض الاحيان ، الإعدام.
If you're living outside like me,
إذا كنت تعيش في الخارج مثلي،
you're faced with life in exile --
تواجه الحياة في المنفى --
the pain of the longing
ألم الشوق
and the separation from your loved ones
والانفصال عن أحبائك
and your family.
وعائلتك.
Therefore, we don't find
ولذلك ، فإننا لا نجد
the moral, emotional,
فضاء معنوي و عاطفي،
psychological and political space
نفسي و سياسي
to distance ourselves from the reality
لنبتعد عن واقع
of social responsibility.
المسؤولية الاجتماعية.
Oddly enough,
ومن الغريب،
an artist such as myself
فنانة مثلي
finds herself also in the position of being the voice,
تجد نفسها أيضا في موقف ان تكون صوت،
the speaker of my people,
المتكلم لشعبي،
even if I have, indeed,
حتى لو كانت، في الواقع ،
no access to my own country.
لا أ ستطيع الوصول إلى بلدي.
Also, people like myself,
أيضا، والناس من أمثالي،
we're fighting two battles on different grounds.
نحن نقاتل في معركتين على جبهتين مختلفتين.
We're being critical of the West,
نحن ننتقد الغرب،
the perception of the West
و نظرة الغرب
about our identity --
حول هويتنا --
about the image that is constructed about us,
حول الصورة التي يتم تشكيلها عنا،
about our women, about our politics,
عن نسائنا، حول سياساتنا،
about our religion.
عن ديننا.
We are there to take pride
نحن هناك لنفخر
and insist on respect.
ونُصرّ على الاحترام.
And at the same time,
وفي الوقت نفسه،
we're fighting another battle.
نحن نقاتل في معركة أخرى.
That is our regime,
وهي مع نظامنا الحاكم،
our government --
حكومتنا --
our atrocious government,
حكومتنا فظيعة،
[that] has done every crime
التي قامت بكل جريمة
in order to stay in power.
من أجل البقاء في السلطة.
Our artists are at risk.
فنانونا في خطر.
We are in a position of danger.
نحن في موقف خطر.
We pose a threat
نحن نشكل تهديدا
to the order of the government.
لنظام الحكم.
But ironically,
ولكن من المفارقات،
this situation
هذا الوضع
has empowered all of us,
مكن كل واحد منا،
because we are considered, as artists,
لأننا نعتبر، نحن كفنانين،
central to the cultural, political,
مركز الثقافة والسياسية،
social discourse in Iran.
الخطاب الاجتماعي في ايران.
We are there to inspire, to provoke,
نحن موجودون هناك لإلهام وإثارة،
to mobilize,
لتعبئة،
to bring hope to our people.
لجلب الأمل لشعبنا.
We are the reporters of our people,
ونحن المبلغين عن شعبنا،
and are communicators
ونصل شعبنا
to the outside world.
بالعالم الخارجي.
Art is our weapon.
الفن هو سلاحنا.
Culture is a form of resistance.
الثقافة هي شكل من أشكال المقاومة.
I envy sometimes the artists of the West
أنا أحسد أحيانا فناني الغرب
for their freedom of expression.
لحقهم في حرية التعبير --
For the fact that they can distance themselves
لحقيقة أنهم يمكن أن ينأوا بأنفسهم
from the question of politics.
عن مسألة السياسة --
From the fact that they are only serving one audience,
من حقيقة أنهم يخدمون جمهور واحد فقط،
mainly the Western culture.
أساسا الثقافة الغربية.
But also, I worry about the West,
ولكن أيضا، وأنا قلقة على الغرب،
because often in this country,
لأن في كثير من الأحيان في هذا البلد،
in this Western world that we have,
في هذا العالم الغربي الذي لدينا،
culture risks being a form of entertainment.
ثقافة المخاطر تكون شكلا من أشكال الترفيه.
Our people depend on our artists,
شعبنا يعتمد على فنانينا،
and culture is beyond communication.
والثقافة اعمق من الاتصال.
My journey as an artist
رحلتي كفنانة
started from a very, very personal place.
فقط من مكان جدا، شخصي جدا.
I did not start
أنا لم أبدأ
to make social commentary
بالتوثيق الاجتماعي
about my country.
عن بلدي.
The first one that you see in front of you
أول واحدة تراها أمامك
is actually when I first returned to Iran
هو في الواقع عندما عدت إلى إيران أول مرة
after being separated for a good 12 years.
بعد انفصال دام لـ 12 سنة جيدة.
It was after the Islamic Revolution
وكان بعد قيام الثورة الإسلامية
of 1979.
عام 1979.
While I was absent from Iran,
بينما كنت غائبة عن إيران،
the Islamic Revolution had descended on Iran
وكانت الثورة الاسلامية في ايران تنحدر
and had entirely transformed the country
وحولت البلاد تماما
from Persian to the Islamic culture.
من الفارسية إلى الثقافة الإسلامية.
I came mainly to be reunited with my family
جئت أساسا لـ لم الشمل مع عائلتي
and to reconnect in a way
وإعادة الاتصال بطريقة
that I found my place in the society.
لأجد مكاني في المجتمع.
But instead, I found a country
لكن بدلا من ذلك، وجدت البلاد
that was totally ideological
عقائدية تماما
and that I didn't recognize anymore.
والتي لم أتعرف عليها بعد.
More so, I became very interested,
أكثر من ذلك ، أصبحت مهتمة جدا،
as I was facing
عندما كنت أواجه
my own personal dilemmas and questions,
معضلاتي الشخصية والأسئلة ،
I became immersed in the study
أصبحت مغمورة في دراسة
of the Islamic Revolution --
للثورة الإسلامية --
how, indeed,
كيف، في الواقع ،
it had incredibly transformed
انها حولت بشكل لايصدق
the lives of Iranian women.
حياة المرأة الإيرانية.
I found the subject of Iranian women
لقد وجدت هذا الموضوع من النساء الإيرانيات
immensely interesting,
مثير للاهتمام للغاية،
in the way the women of Iran, historically,
بطريقة ما المرأة في إيران، تاريخيا،
seemed to embody the political transformation.
تجسد التحول السياسي.
So in a way, by studying a woman,
ذلك بطريقة ما ، من خلال دراسة امرأة،
you can read the structure and the ideology of the country.
يمكنك قراءة تركيبة وفكر البلاد.
So I made a group of work
لذلك كونت مجموعة عمل
that at once faced my own personal questions in life,
لمواجهة الأسئلة التي واجهتها في حياتي الشخصية،
and yet it brought my work into a larger discourse --
ومع ذلك ، قدمت عملي بخطاب اكبر --
the subject of martyrdom,
موضوع الاستشهاد ،
the question of those who willingly stand in that intersection
السؤال من الذين يقفون في ذلك التقاطع عن طيب خاطر
of love of God, faith,
لمحبة الله، والإيمان ،
but violence and crime and cruelty.
وكذلك العنف والجريمة والقسوة.
For me, this became incredibly important.
بالنسبة لي ، أصبح هذا مهم للغاية.
And yet, I had an unusual position toward this.
وحتى الآن ، كان لي موقف غير عادي نحو هذا.
I was an outsider
كنت الدخيلة
who had come back to Iran to find my place,
التي كانت قد عادت الى ايران لايجاد مكاني،
but I was not in a position
ولكن لم أكن في وضع يسمح
to be critical of the government
بأن أنتقد الحكومة
or the ideology of the Islamic Revolution.
أو إيديولوجية الثورة الاسلامية.
This changed slowly
تغيير هذا ببطء
as I found my voice
كما وجدت صوتي
and I discovered things
واكتشفت أشياء
that I didn't know I would discover.
لم أكن أعلم أنني سوف اكتشف.
So my art became slightly more critical.
لذلك أصبح فني نوعا ما أكثر احراجا.
My knife became a little sharper.
أصبحت سكيني أكثر حدة.
And I fell into a life in exile.
ولقد وقعت في حياة المنفى.
I am a nomadic artist.
أنا فنان رحال.
I work in Morocco, in Turkey, in Mexico.
أنا أعمل في المغرب، في تركيا، في المكسيك.
I go everywhere to make believe it's Iran.
في كل مكان أذهب اليه لجعلها ايران.
Now I am making films.
الآن أنا اصنع الأفلام.
Last year, I finished a film
وفي العام الماضي، انتهيت من فيلم
called "Women Without Men."
يدعى "نساء بلا رجال".
"Women Without Men" returns to history,
"نساء بلا رجال" يعود الى التاريخ،
but another part of our Iranian history.
ولكن آخر جزء من تاريخنا الايراني.
It goes to 1953
يعود الى 1953
when American CIA exercised a coup
عندما قامت وكالة المخابرات المركزية الأمريكية بانقلاب
and removed a democratically elected leader,
وإزالة الزعيم المنتخب ديمقراطيا،
Dr. Mossadegh.
الدكتور مصدق.
The book is written by an Iranian woman,
الكتاب هو مكتوب من قبل امرأة إيرانية،
Shahrnush Parsipur.
شاهرنوش باريسبور.
It's a magical realist novel.
انها رواية واقعية ساحرة.
This book is banned,
وحظر هذا الكتاب،
and she spent five years in prison.
وأمضت خمس سنوات في السجن.
My obsession with this book,
هاجسي مع هذا الكتاب ،
and the reason I made this into a film,
كان السبب الذي جعلني اصور هذا الفيلم،
is because it at once was addressing
لأنه كان يتحدث في وقت واحد
the question of being a female --
مسألة كونها أنثى --
traditionally, historically in Iran --
تقليديا وتاريخيا في إيران --
and the question of four women
ومسألة أربع نساء
who are all looking for an idea
يبحثن عن فكرة
of change, freedom and democracy --
الحرية والتغيير والديمقراطية --
while the country of Iran, equally, as if another character,
في حين أن إيران بلد، على حد سواء ، كما شخص آخر،
also struggled for an idea
تكافح أيضا لفكرة
of freedom and democracy
الحرية والديمقراطية
and independence from the foreign interventions.
واستقلاله من التدخلات الخارجية.
I made this film
صنعت هذا الفيلم
because I felt it's important
لأنني شعرت أنه من المهم
for it to speak to the Westerners
التحدث الى الغربيين
about our history as a country.
حول تاريخنا كدولة.
That all of you seem to remember Iran
انكم جميعا تذكرون ايران
after the Islamic Revolution.
بعد الثورة الإسلامية.
That Iran was once a secular society,
ايران كانت مرة ما مجتمع علماني،
and we had democracy,
وكان لدينا ديمقراطية،
and this democracy was stolen from us
وسرقت هذه الديمقراطية منا
by the American government,
من قبل الحكومة الأمريكية ،
by the British government.
من قبل الحكومة البريطانية.
This film also speaks to the Iranian people
هذا الفيلم يتحدث أيضا للشعب الايراني
in asking them to return to their history
يطلب منهم العودة الى تاريخهم
and look at themselves before they were so Islamicized --
وإلقاء نظرة على أنفسهم أنهم كانوا قبل ذلك التشدد الديني --
in the way we looked, in the way we played music,
في الطريقة التي ننظر في طريقة عزفنا الموسيقى ،
in the way we had intellectual life.
في الطريقة التي أثرت الحياة الفكرية.
And most of all,
والأهم من ذلك كله،
in the way that we fought for democracy.
في الطريقة التي حاربنا بها من أجل الديمقراطية.
These are some of the shots actually from my film.
هذه هي بعض من اللقطات من فيلمي.
These are some of the images of the coup.
هذه هي بعض من صور الانقلاب.
And we made this film in Casablanca,
صنعنا هذا الفيلم في الدار البيضاء،
recreating all the shots.
جميع اللقطات.
This film tried to find a balance
حاول هذا الفيلم من أجل إيجاد توازن
between telling a political story,
بين ان تحكي قصة سياسية،
but also a feminine story.
ولكن أيضا قصة الأنثى.
Being a visual artist, indeed,
كوني فنانة بصرية، في الواقع ،
I am foremost interested to make art --
أنا مهتم قبل كل شيء لجعل الفن --
to make art that transcends
لجعل الفن الذي يسمو
politics, religion,
السياسة والدين،
the question of feminism,
مسألة النسوية،
and become an important, timeless,
واصبحت مهمة، خالدة،
universal work of art.
عمل فني عالمي.
The challenge I have
التحدي لدي
is how to do that.
هو كيف نفعل ذلك --
How to tell a political story but an allegorical story.
كيف تروي قصة سياسية قصة استعارية --
How to move you with your emotions,
كيفية تحريك عواطفكم،
but also make your mind work.
ولكن أيضا جعل عقلك يعمل.
These are some of the images
هذه هي بعض من الصور
and the characters of the film.
وشخصيات الفيلم.
Now comes the green movement --
الآن تأتي الحركة الخضراء --
the summer of 2009,
صيف عام 2009،
as my film is released --
كما صدر فيلمي --
the uprising begins in the streets of Tehran.
تبدأ الانتفاضة في شوارع طهران.
What is unbelievably ironic
ما يثير السخرية بشكل لا يصدق
is the period that we tried to depict in the film,
هي الفترة التي حاولنا فيها تصوير فيلم ،
the cry for democracy
صرخة من أجل الديمقراطية
and social justice,
والعدالة الاجتماعية،
repeats itself now
يعيد نفسه الآن
again in Tehran.
مرة أخرى في طهران.
The green movement
الحركة الخضراء
significantly inspired the world.
مستوحاة بشكل كبير من العالم.
It brought a lot of attention to all those Iranians
انها جلبت الكثير من الانتباه لجميع أولئك الإيرانيين
who stand for basic human rights
الذين يقفون من أجل حقوق الإنسان الأساسية
and struggle for democracy.
والنضال من أجل الديمقراطية.
What was most significant for me
ما هو أهم بالنسبة لي
was, once again,
وكان، مرة أخرى،
the presence of the women.
وجود المرأة.
They're absolutely inspirational for me.
انهم ملهمة للغاية بالنسبة لي.
If in the Islamic Revolution,
واذا كان في الثورة الإسلامية ،
the images of the woman portrayed
صورت صور الامرأة
were submissive
المنقادة
and didn't have a voice,
ولم يكن لها صوت،
now we saw a new idea of feminism
نرأى نحن الآن فكرة جديدة عن النساء
in the streets of Tehran --
في شوارع طهران --
women who were educated,
النساء الذين تلقوا تعليمهم،
forward thinking, non-traditional,
تقدميات التفكير ، وغير تقليديات ،
sexually open, fearless
منفتحات جنسيا ، لا يعرفن الخوف
and seriously feminist.
نسوة جديات.
These women and those young men
هؤلاء النساء وهؤلاء الشبان
united Iranians
وحدوا الايرانيين
across the world, inside and outside.
في جميع أنحاء العالم، في الداخل والخارج.
I then discovered
ثم اكتشفت
why I take so much inspiration
لماذا لدي الكثير من الإلهام
from Iranian women.
من النساء الإيرانيات.
That, under all circumstances,
ذلك ، في جميع الظروف ،
they have pushed the boundary.
لقد دفعن الحدود.
They have confronted the authority.
وواجهن تلك السلطة.
They have broken every rule
وحطمن كل القيود
in the smallest and the biggest way.
في أصغر وأكبر وسيلة.
And once again, they proved themselves.
ومرة أخرى، أثبتن أنهن أنفسهن.
I stand here to say
أقف هنا لأقول
that Iranian women have found a new voice,
لقد وجدت النساء الإيرانيات صوت جديد،
and their voice is giving me my voice.
وصوتهن اعطاني صوتي.
And it's a great honor
وإنه لشرف عظيم
to be an Iranian woman and an Iranian artist,
أن تكون امرأة إيرانية وفنانة إيرانية،
even if I have to operate in the West only for now.
حتى لو أن تعمل في الغرب فقط في الوقت الراهن.
Thank you so much.
شكرا جزيلا لكم.
(Applause)
(تصفيق)